<!-- $Id: dbmanager.xml,v 1.6 2005/05/11 13:12:12 unsaved Exp $ -->

<appendix>
<title>Database Manager</title>
<appendixinfo>
    <authorgroup>
        <author>
            <firstname>Fred</firstname><surname>Toussi</surname>
            <email>&fredaddr;</email>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>HSQLDB Development Group</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
        <author>
            <firstname>Blaine</firstname><surname>Simpson</surname>
            <email>&blaineaddr;</email>
            <affiliation>
                <orgname>HSQLDB Development Group</orgname>
            </affiliation>
        </author>
    </authorgroup>
    <edition>$Revision: 1.6 $</edition>
    <pubdate>$Date: 2005/05/11 13:12:12 $</pubdate>
    <keywordset>
        <keyword>Hsqldb</keyword>
        <keyword>Database</keyword>
        <keyword>Manager</keyword>
    </keywordset>
</appendixinfo>

<section>
    <title>Brief Introduction</title>
    <para>The Database Manager tool is a simple GUI database query tool with a 
	tree display of the tables. Both AWT and SWING versions of the tool are
	available and work almost identically. The AWT version class name is
	org.hsqldb.util.DatabaseManager; the SWING version,
	org.hsqldb.util.DatabaseManagerSwing. 
	</para><para>
	The AWT version of the database manager can be deployed as an applet in
	a browser. A demo HTML file with an embedded Database Manager is included
	in the /demo directory.
	</para><para>
	When the Database Manager is started, a dialogue allows you to
	enter the JDBC driver, URL, user and password for the new connection.
	A drop-down box, Type, offers preset values for JDBC driver and URL for
	most popular database engines, including HSQLDB. Once you have selected
	an item from this drop-down box, you should edit the URL to specify
	the details of the database or any additional properties to pass. You should
	also enter the username and password before clicking on the OK button. 	
	</para><para>
	The AWT connection dialogue allows you to save the settings for the connection
	you are about to make. You can then access the connection in future sessions.
	To save a connection setting, enter a name in the Setting Name box before
	clicking on the OK button. Next time the connection dialogue is displayed,
	the drop-down box labeled Recent will include the name for all the saved
	connection settings. When you select a name, the individual settings are
	displayed in the appropriate boxes.
	</para><para>
	The small Clr button next to the drop-down box allows you to clear all the
	saved settings. If you want to modify an existing setting, first select
	it from the drop-down box then modify any of the text boxes before making
	the connection. The modified values will be saved.
	</para>
    <simpara>
        Most menu items have context-sensitive tool tip help text which 
        will appear if you hold the mouse cursor still over the desired 
        menu item.
        (Assuming that you don't turn Tooltips off under the
        <guimenu>Help</guimenu> menu.
    </simpara>
    <simpara>
        The DatabaseManagers do work with HSQLDB servers serving 
        TLS-encrypted JDBC data.
        See the <link linkend='tls-chapter' endterm='tls-title'/> chapter and
        the <link linkend='auth-section' endterm='auth-title'/> section of
        this Guide.
    </simpara>
</section> 
<section>
    <title>Auto tree-update</title>
    <simpara>
        By default, the object tree in the left panel is refreshed when
        you execute DDL which may update those objects.
        If you are on a slow network or performance-challenged PC, use the
        <guimenu>view</guimenu> / <guimenuitem>Auto-refresh tree</guimenuitem>
        menu item to turn it off.
        You will then need to use the
        <guimenu>view</guimenu><guimenuitem>Refresh tree</guimenuitem> menu 
        item every time that you want to refresh the tree.
    </simpara>
    <note><simpara>
        Auto-refresh tree does not automatically show all updates to
        database objects, it only refreshes when you submit DDL which may
        update database objects.
        (This behavior is a compromise between utility and performance).
    </simpara></note>
</section>
<section>
    <title>Automatic Connection</title>
    <para>
        You can use command-line switches to supply connection information.
        If you use these switch(es), then the connection dialog window will
        be skipped and a JDBC connection will be established immediately.
        Assuming that the hsqldb.jar (or an alternative jar) are in your
        CLASSPATH, this command will list the available command-line options.
        <informalexample><screen>
    java org.hsqldb.util.DatabaseManagerSwing --help</screen>
        </informalexample>
    </para><simpara>
        It's convenient to skip the connection dialog window if you always
        work with the same database account.
    </simpara> <warning><simpara>
        Use of the --password switch is not secure.
        Everything typed on command-lines is generally available to other
        users on the computer.
        The problem is compounded if you use a network connection to 
        obtain your command line.
        The RC File section explains how you can set up automatic
        connections without supplying a password on the command line.
    </simpara></warning>
</section>
<section>
    <title>RC File</title>
    <simpara>
        You can skip the connection dialog window securely by putting
        the connection information into an RC file and then using the
        <literal>--urlid</literal> switch to DatabaseManager or
        DatabaseManagerSwing.
        This strategy is great for adding launch menu items and/or launch 
        icons to your desktop.
        You can set up one icon for each of the database accounts which
        you regularly use.
    </simpara> <simpara>
        The default location for the RC file is 
        <filename>dbmanager.rc</filename> in your home directory.
        The <link linkend='auth-section' endterm='auth-title'/> section 
        explains how to put the connection information into this text file.
        If you also run 
        <link linkend='sqltool-chapter' endterm='sqltool-title'/>, then
        you can share the RC file with SqlTool by using a sym-link (if
        your operating system supports sym links), or by using the
        <literal>--rcfile</literal> switch for either SqlTool or
        DatabaseManagerSwing.
    </simpara><warning><simpara>
        Use your operating system facilities to prevent others from reading
        your RC file, since it contains passwords.
    </simpara></warning>
    <simpara>
        To set up launch items/icons, first experiment on your command
        line to find exactly what command works.  For example,
        <informalexample><screen>
    java -cp /path/to/hsqldb.jar org.hsqldb.util.DatabaseManagerSwing --urlid mem</screen>
        </informalexample>
        Then, use your window manager to add an item that runs this command.
    </simpara>
</section>
    <section>
        <title>
            Updating your old HSQLDB distrubution to use the current
            DatabaseManagers
        </title>
        <simpara>This procedure will allow users of a legacy version of
            HSQLDB to use all of the new features of the DatabaseManagers.
            You will also get the new versions of the SqlTool!
            This procedure works for distros going back to 1.7.3.3 at least,
            probably much farther.
        </simpara>
        <procedure>
            <step><simpara>
                Copy these files from src/org/hsqldb/util of the current
                HSQLDB distribution to the same directory within your
                new distribution: <literal>DatabaseMan* SqlTool*
                SqlFile* RCData* *Swing.java *.gif *.png</literal>
            </simpara></step><step><simpara>
                cd to the build directory of your new distro and run
                <literal>ant clean</literal>
            </simpara></step><step><simpara>
                <literal>ant classes</literal>
            </simpara></step><step><simpara>
                <literal>
                    cp -p ../src/org/hsqldb/util/*.gif
                    ../src/org/hsqldb/util/*.png ../classes/org/hsqldb/util
                </literal>
                </simpara><simpara>
                    Windows users will obviously need to adjust the copy
                    command.
            </simpara></step><step><simpara>
                <literal>ant jar</literal>
            </simpara></step>
        </procedure>
    </section>
</appendix>
